<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-31T15:11:33+00:00</updated><id>https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/</id><title type="html">()=&amp;gt;{} | Void’s blog</title><subtitle>t.b.d.</subtitle><author><name>Maciej Małecki</name></author><entry><title type="html">New PSU for Commodore 64/128</title><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/new-psu-for-c64" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New PSU for Commodore 64/128" /><published>2018-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/new-psu-for-c64</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/new-psu-for-c64">&lt;p&gt;Today I would like to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliability of original C64 CPU has been disputed in community for long time. Commodore had problems with it in the past, plenty of houses were put in fire because of it. Today, over 35 years after first Commodore 64 was produced another issue becomes especially painful: some of bricks decide now to ignore its spec and generate voltage that exceeds its nominal 5VDC thus frying most of precious chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original PSU is not easy to replace. Commodore decided that C64 must be powered with two types of voltages: 9VAC that is then rectified and regulated by circuit located inside computer and 5VDC that is rectified and regulated by circuit iside power brick and is used &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; to power most of C64 chips. This second power line is actually critical, because any deviation from pretty narrow voltage range can either cause unstable operation or damage certain chips (or even all of them). Regulation circuit located inside brick proves to do this devastating job very well. For even more exciting details just check &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.c64-wiki.com/wiki/Power_Supply&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; excellent source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/img/psu-rs/psu-comparison.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Comparison with original units&quot; title=&quot;Comparison with original units&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Various units, from left: Ismet supply (“breadbin”), Ismet supply (early C64C), Dee Van unit (C64 short board) and a brand new PSU replacement by &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:raf@c64power.com&quot;&gt;Rafał Szyja&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t exaggerate if I say that using the same PSU for more than 30 years is like playing Russian Roulette. We definitely needs some…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;alternatives&quot;&gt;…alternatives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of alternate solutions available, unfortunatelly most of them are DIY, and not everybody have sufficient skills for that. And if have and do something wrong, you may kill a patient. Too bad… Let’s look briefly at options that we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;power-savers&quot;&gt;Power savers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power Saver is an additional overvoltage protection that is plugged between PSU and computer (can be also mounted inside the computer). I think that original idea came from &lt;a href=&quot;http://personalpages.tds.net/~rcarlsen/cbm/c64/SAVER/&quot;&gt;Ray Carlsen&lt;/a&gt; as he got more and more damaged C64s due to PSU malfunction. In its simplest form this is electro-mechanical device using relay that turns off 5V DC line when some predefined threshold (i.e. 5.4V) is meet. Ray never claimed that saver is “the final and best solution” - it’s rather workaround of a problem - you can still use your PSU while waiting for new replacement. With saver and original old PSU there is still a risk, that circuit and relay will not react fast enough to save your electronics, if regulator gets badly shorted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it still makes sense to use saver while using switching PSU replacement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;After-market power supplies, even switching types, can fail at any time. Switchers are more reliable and much less prone to catastrophic failures but can still cause damage to the computer if they fail. This Saver is designed to protect any computer that uses the standard Commodore “brick” power supply as well as any newer switch-mode PS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;replace-linear-regulator&quot;&gt;Replace linear regulator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty easy DIY fix that someone suggested in Facebook discussion: if you’re lucky enough to disassemble your original PSU, you can replace linear regulator with switching regulator such as 5V UBEC, commonly used to power electronics onboard of RC models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bundle-two-market-adapters&quot;&gt;Bundle two market adapters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buy-new-working-unit&quot;&gt;Buy new working unit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;test-of-new-psu-replacement&quot;&gt;Test of new PSU replacement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/img/psu-rs/psu-overview.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PSU from Rafał Szyja&quot; title=&quot;Overview of PSU&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Light colors of PSU fits well with C64C beige case&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit is not particularily small. In fact it is bigger than any of original PSUs that are in my possesion (refer first figure). This is partially because manufacturer decides not to produce dedicated case but to use generic one that is available on the market. Most importantly, we have two power supply units here in fact, bundled in one package. Bigger case also improves cooling, which was actually a weak point of original PSU. Here in fact, I haven’t observed any noticeable heat production, which is very promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;testing&quot;&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My test run started with set that should draw much current out of 5VDC line: short boarded C64C with 1541UltimateII+. For Ultimate cartridge I do not use auxiliary power supply, so PSU must provide whole power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/img/psu-rs/C64C-E-1541U2-REU.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;C64C with 1541U2+&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;C64C and 1541Ultimate II+ running 16MB REU demo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the combination I used most of the time. I have noticed no instabilities or other reliability problems. PSU run cool and silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I have replaced 1541U with real 1541II drive. I deliberately left PSU on the desk, lying nearby floppy drive so see whether it may produce any significant interference that may influence the drive. This time I have also no problems - both C64 and 1541II run stable and PSU stayed cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/img/psu-rs/C64C-E-1541.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;C64 with 1541II&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;C64C and real 1541II running the Edge of Disgrace by Booze&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also used this PSU with C64 (Assy 250407) and 1541 “toaster”. With this version more chips are using 9VAC line. There was apparently no difference in PSU behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/img/psu-rs/C64-breadbin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Breadbin with toaster&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;C64 Breadbin and 1541 Toaster&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last set I have assembled for this test was C64C with long board connected with 1541 resembling “C” model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/img/psu-rs/C64C-B3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;C64C B3 with 1541&amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Best looking C64;-) also had no problems with this PSU&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name>Maciej Małecki</name></author><summary type="html">Today I would like to Introduction Reliability of original C64 CPU has been disputed in community for long time. Commodore had problems with it in the past, plenty of houses were put in fire because of it. Today, over 35 years after first Commodore 64 was produced another issue becomes especially painful: some of bricks decide now to ignore its spec and generate voltage that exceeds its nominal 5VDC thus frying most of precious chips. Original PSU is not easy to replace. Commodore decided that C64 must be powered with two types of voltages: 9VAC that is then rectified and regulated by circuit located inside computer and 5VDC that is rectified and regulated by circuit iside power brick and is used directly to power most of C64 chips. This second power line is actually critical, because any deviation from pretty narrow voltage range can either cause unstable operation or damage certain chips (or even all of them). Regulation circuit located inside brick proves to do this devastating job very well. For even more exciting details just check this excellent source. Various units, from left: Ismet supply (“breadbin”), Ismet supply (early C64C), Dee Van unit (C64 short board) and a brand new PSU replacement by Rafał Szyja I wouldn’t exaggerate if I say that using the same PSU for more than 30 years is like playing Russian Roulette. We definitely needs some… …alternatives There are plenty of alternate solutions available, unfortunatelly most of them are DIY, and not everybody have sufficient skills for that. And if have and do something wrong, you may kill a patient. Too bad… Let’s look briefly at options that we have: Power savers Power Saver is an additional overvoltage protection that is plugged between PSU and computer (can be also mounted inside the computer). I think that original idea came from Ray Carlsen as he got more and more damaged C64s due to PSU malfunction. In its simplest form this is electro-mechanical device using relay that turns off 5V DC line when some predefined threshold (i.e. 5.4V) is meet. Ray never claimed that saver is “the final and best solution” - it’s rather workaround of a problem - you can still use your PSU while waiting for new replacement. With saver and original old PSU there is still a risk, that circuit and relay will not react fast enough to save your electronics, if regulator gets badly shorted. However, it still makes sense to use saver while using switching PSU replacement: After-market power supplies, even switching types, can fail at any time. Switchers are more reliable and much less prone to catastrophic failures but can still cause damage to the computer if they fail. This Saver is designed to protect any computer that uses the standard Commodore “brick” power supply as well as any newer switch-mode PS. Replace linear regulator This is pretty easy DIY fix that someone suggested in Facebook discussion: if you’re lucky enough to disassemble your original PSU, you can replace linear regulator with switching regulator such as 5V UBEC, commonly used to power electronics onboard of RC models. Bundle two market adapters Buy new working unit Test of new PSU replacement Light colors of PSU fits well with C64C beige case The unit is not particularily small. In fact it is bigger than any of original PSUs that are in my possesion (refer first figure). This is partially because manufacturer decides not to produce dedicated case but to use generic one that is available on the market. Most importantly, we have two power supply units here in fact, bundled in one package. Bigger case also improves cooling, which was actually a weak point of original PSU. Here in fact, I haven’t observed any noticeable heat production, which is very promising. Testing My test run started with set that should draw much current out of 5VDC line: short boarded C64C with 1541UltimateII+. For Ultimate cartridge I do not use auxiliary power supply, so PSU must provide whole power. C64C and 1541Ultimate II+ running 16MB REU demo This is the combination I used most of the time. I have noticed no instabilities or other reliability problems. PSU run cool and silent. Next, I have replaced 1541U with real 1541II drive. I deliberately left PSU on the desk, lying nearby floppy drive so see whether it may produce any significant interference that may influence the drive. This time I have also no problems - both C64 and 1541II run stable and PSU stayed cool. C64C and real 1541II running the Edge of Disgrace by Booze I have also used this PSU with C64 (Assy 250407) and 1541 “toaster”. With this version more chips are using 9VAC line. There was apparently no difference in PSU behavior. C64 Breadbin and 1541 Toaster Last set I have assembled for this test was C64C with long board connected with 1541 resembling “C” model. Best looking C64;-) also had no problems with this PSU Summary</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/welcome-to-jekyll" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2018-01-29T13:39:08+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T13:39:08+00:00</updated><id>https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/welcome-to-jekyll">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Maciej Małecki</name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated. To add new posts, simply add a file in the _posts directory that follows the convention YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works. Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets: def print_hi(name) puts &quot;Hi, #{name}&quot;endprint_hi('Tom')#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT. Check out the Jekyll docs for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at Jekyll’s GitHub repo. If you have questions, you can ask them on Jekyll Talk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TheReviewIndex | Unbiased User Review Summaries | Monochrome</title><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/thereviewindex-introduction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TheReviewIndex | Unbiased User Review Summaries | Monochrome" /><published>2017-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/thereviewindex-introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/thereviewindex-introduction">&lt;p&gt;The internet is a source of a humongous amount of unstructured content for all sorts of products, in the form of blogs, videos, user and expert reviews, etc. It is almost impossible for anyone to scour all of this disparate data, with contradictory opinions, and thereafter make a correct, or at least optimal, purchase decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, the main problem any average consumer faces while trying to research products online is that there are too many sites with far too much information, and there is typically a disparity in the various opinions expressed. Also, it is not easy to differentiate between what is genuine, and what isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help resolve these issues, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com&quot;&gt;The Review Index&lt;/a&gt; has launched its discovery and research engine, which simplifies the process of researching products online. It scours various sources on the internet, and mines opinions and reviews for the products. This information is then presented as a unified, unbiased, feature-wise summary scorecard of the aggregate opinion to the end user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leveraging cutting-edge Machine Learning Algorithms and Artificial Neural Networks, The Review Index compiles reviews from popular sources which are relevant, and focuses on detection of fine-grained topics and sentiment implied therein. It focuses on evaluating the pros and cons as indicated by the reviewers, while ensuring that fraudulent content is identified and removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public beta was launched in January 2017 with six product categories, which include &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com/mobiles&quot;&gt;Mobiles&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com/speakers&quot;&gt;Speakers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com/televisions&quot;&gt;Televisions&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com/routers&quot;&gt;Routers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com/microwaves&quot;&gt;Microwaves&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thereviewindex.com/washingmachines&quot;&gt;Washing Machines&lt;/a&gt; and caters to Indian consumers. Reviews from popular online stores are compiled and reconciled using Neural Network based algorithms, and feature-wise summaries of the aggregated opinion is created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, this search engine enables users to discover the optimal products, which satisfy their various requirements. The users are also provided with access to feature-wise ratings, summary, list of pros and cons, as well as user comment snippets. Eventually, the engine compares the prices for the displayed products across all the online stores, to conclude which one has the most cost-effective offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is to expand to more categories such as electronics, home appliances, etc. in the near future, while at the same time expanding the sources of opinions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Maciej Małecki</name></author><summary type="html">The internet is a source of a humongous amount of unstructured content for all sorts of products, in the form of blogs, videos, user and expert reviews, etc. It is almost impossible for anyone to scour all of this disparate data, with contradictory opinions, and thereafter make a correct, or at least optimal, purchase decision.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Typography Example | Monochrome</title><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/typography-example" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Typography Example | Monochrome" /><published>2017-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/typography-example</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/typography-example">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/monochrome/img/img-test.png&quot; alt=&quot;Test&quot; title=&quot;Test&quot; /&gt;
Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.example.com&quot;&gt;consectetur adipisicing&lt;/a&gt; elit. Id, aliquam magni et officiis nemo nihil aliquid placeat alias. Eum voluptates ducimus, nobis ex illum laboriosam quidem corrupti impedit ratione in voluptatum amet beatae facilis temporibus voluptate praesentium voluptatibus! At ab, iusto error amet eveniet debitis ipsa recusandae possimus minima sunt itaque, nulla ducimus officia, consequatur ipsum laudantium magnam hic fuga vero incidunt nostrum. Commodi, perspiciatis ut nostrum fugit nulla cumque voluptate harum nemo accusamus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-a-h2&quot;&gt;This is a h2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;h3-h4-h5-and-h6-have-the-same-style&quot;&gt;h3, h4, h5 and h6 have the same style.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisicing elit. Voluptas sed quo atque &lt;em&gt;perspiciatis&lt;/em&gt;. Eius cum possimus, maxime unde, asperiores neque blanditiis molestiae ipsa odit. &lt;strong&gt;Laboriosam&lt;/strong&gt;, error! Ipsa officia magnam at ratione commodi porro nulla consequuntur eum quia nisi officiis cupiditate reprehenderit provident facilis rem, nobis quidem fugiat, et! Tempore maiores reprehenderit laboriosam rerum?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a blockquote&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unordered-list&quot;&gt;Unordered list&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list 3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ordered-list&quot;&gt;Ordered list&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;three&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;four&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Maciej Małecki</name></author><summary type="html">Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisicing elit. Id, aliquam magni et officiis nemo nihil aliquid placeat alias. Eum voluptates ducimus, nobis ex illum laboriosam quidem corrupti impedit ratione in voluptatum amet beatae facilis temporibus voluptate praesentium voluptatibus! At ab, iusto error amet eveniet debitis ipsa recusandae possimus minima sunt itaque, nulla ducimus officia, consequatur ipsum laudantium magnam hic fuga vero incidunt nostrum. Commodi, perspiciatis ut nostrum fugit nulla cumque voluptate harum nemo accusamus?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Code Example</title><link href="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/code-example" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Code Example" /><published>2017-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/code-example</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://maciejmalecki.github.io/blog/code-example">&lt;p&gt;To insert highlight code inside of a post, it’s enough to use some specific tags, has directly described into the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/templates/#code-snippet-highlighting&quot;&gt;Jekyll documentation&lt;/a&gt;. In this way the code will be included into a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.highlight&lt;/code&gt; CSS class and will be highlight according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/tpw/blob/master/css/syntax.css&quot;&gt;syntax.scss&lt;/a&gt; file. This is the standard style adopted by &lt;strong&gt;Github&lt;/strong&gt; to highlight the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a CSS example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot; data-lang=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;2&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;3&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;4&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;5&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;6&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;7&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;8&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#fff&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;h1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#ffaa33&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;1.5em&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a HTML example, with a linenumber:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;2&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;3&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;example.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Example&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, a Ruby example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;2&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;3&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;hello&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello World!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br data-jekyll-commonmark-ghpages=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Maciej Małecki</name></author><summary type="html">To insert highlight code inside of a post, it’s enough to use some specific tags, has directly described into the Jekyll documentation. In this way the code will be included into a .highlight CSS class and will be highlight according to the syntax.scss file. This is the standard style adopted by Github to highlight the code.</summary></entry></feed>